Okay, so let's talk about the differences
then between leaders and managers.
Now, before we actually talk about the
differences, right, understand that the
project manager is the visionary leader
for the project.
Right, so project manager in a predictive
project, right?
Remember, they are the command and control
project manager.
They are the ones that are accountable for
all the work that goes on the project.
They are the ones that are leading the
team.
They are leading the project.
So they are the visionary leaders of the
project.
They promote the direction of the project.
They are the ones that collaborate with
team members, collaborate
with stakeholders.
They're making sure things are moving
along.
They're performing all of the planning.
They're doing all of the planning.
And with team members, of course, with
other stakeholders and other team members.
So again, they are collaborating with
other.
other team members and other stakeholders,
right, removing any issues, removing any
impediments to success and so and so
forth, right?
So they are the visionary leader of the
project.
They're making sure the project is moving
along and it is meeting the strategic
direction of the organization,
right?
The project is in line with the strategic
direction of the organization and the
project is in line with the original scope
of the project.
The project is not going off on a tangent
somewhere, right?
We're not having runaway costs and, you
know, runaway timelines
and so and so forth.
On an agile project, it's a team that is
responsible for the leadership.
So, the team as a whole,
whereas in a predictive
project, the project managers
and that's responsible.
Now, let's talk about then the basic
differences between leaders and managers.
There are many, many, many types of
leaders, many, many types of managers.
So you can spend an entire class just
discussing the differences between leaders
and managers and
all the different styles of
leadership and all the
different styles of management.
That's an entire topic by itself.
You obviously don't need that level of
detail for the PMP exam, but you just need
to know the basic differences between
leaders and managers.
So overall, the basic
differences, right, managers
generally would be
considered more taskmasters.
They are basically making sure that tasks
are being done, things are moving along,
they're focused on
satisfying stakeholders needs,
so they're more short-term
tactical decision-making.
They have a goal.
Managers always have their goal and that's
what they're focused on.
They're not looking at the overall
organization or how this goal fits in with
the overall organization, this is their
goal.
And a manager then is more in a delegating
role.
A manager will say, you do this,
you do this, you do this.
A leader, on the other hand, they still
want all of those tasks to be complete,
but a leader is looking more long-term
strategic decision-making.
They are looking at more the long-term
strategic vision of the organisation,
and making long-term strategic decisions
about the organisation.
So they're not just looking
at one piece, manager,
they're just looking at
their one portion, one piece.
That's what they're concentrating on.
Whereas leaders are looking at the entire
organisation as a whole.
They're looking at how
this piece impacts the
organisation, how this piece
impacts the organisation.
They're looking at it overall.
Whereas a manager is
more in a delegating role,
like you do this, you
do this, you do this.
leader, right, will not say you do this,
you do this.
A leader will be more a case of saying,
well, what do you think we should do?
And why do you think we should do that?
And then based on that, they make a
decision.
They make a strategic decision about the
project.
So managers then are more short-term
tactical decision-making, right,
leaders are more long-term vision,
right?
So a leader will say, this is where we
need to get to.
So a manager, on the other hand, we'll
be figuring out how do we get to that?
They're more short-term tactical
decision-making.
Leaders are more, like I said,
long-term strategic.
So that's a basic, high-level basic
difference in leaders and managers.
So managers then are going to maintain,
right, because they're looking at,
you know, their own piece.
So they're more short-term
decision-making.
So managers are going to
maintain, leaders develop,
right, because they're
looking more long-term.
Managers administrate, right?
They follow a procedure.
Leaders innovate.
They create those procedures, right,
if you're like.
Managers are going to ask how and when,
whereas leaders are
going to ask what and why.
So what do you think we should do?
Why do you think we should do that?
A leader is going to say, we need to get
to this point.
a manager is going to figure out how do we
get to that point and when do we get to
that point managers generally will accept
the status quo not always I mean as a
general rule whereas leaders will always
challenge the status quo we need to do
something better whereas a manager might
say you know if it's not broken don't fix
it a leader will say let's
improve it and that's all about
innovation so managers rely on
control and following procedures
that's what they're
going to be doing Right.
So a good manager will always follow the
procedures for the organisation,
whereas leaders are going to be developing
those procedures.
So leaders are going to be inspiring
trust.
They are based on trust.
People follow them because they trust
them.
Managers, as I mentioned, they delegate.
They delegate.
You do this.
Whereas leaders will be more influencing
and guiding.
What do you think we should do?
Why do you think we should do that?
They want to understand the other people.
people's point of view, and then based on
that, they will make a decision.
Now that says there's
many, many different types
of leaders, many different
types of managers.
And there's other basic differences
between leaders and managers as well,
which, you know, I'm sure you know,
or you can always look up.
But this is kind of like the high level
basic difference.
So about as much as what you
need to know about as much as
what you need to understand
when it comes to the PMP exam.